在制作蓝色星球Ⅱ的过程中
In the course of making Blue Planet II,
我们探遍了海底世界的每一个角落
we've explored every corner of the underwater world.
我们遇到了不可思议的动物
We've encountered extraordinary animals,
并且对于生命如何在水下生活 有了新的见解
and discovered new insights into how life is lived beneath the waves.
许多年以来 我们都以为海洋浩瀚无穷
For years we thought that the oceans were so vast
海洋生物无数
and the inhabitants so infinitely numerous
所以我们怎样都不会对它们造成影响
that nothing we could do could have an effect upon them.
可如今我们意识到我们错了
But now we know that was wrong.
海洋正面临着人类史上前所未有的威胁
The oceans are under threat now as never before in human history.
在最后一集里
In this final episode,
我们将与试图扭转乾坤的先驱者们对话
we will meet the pioneers who are striving to turn things around.
那些人正致力于保护海洋
People who are helping to save the ocean's most vulnerable inhabitants
以及拯救海洋中最脆弱生物
and dedicating their lives to protecting the seas.
但这一切还来得及吗
But is time running out?
许多人认为我们的海洋已经接近危机边缘了
Many people believe that our oceans have reached a crisis point.
那么究竟 我们的蓝色星球有多脆弱呢
So just how fragile is our blue planet?
冬日的北极圈
Winter in the Arctic Circle.
每一年 挪威的水域都拥有
Every year, the waters of Norway are the setting
最壮丽的野生海洋生物奇观之一
for one of the greatest wildlife spectacles in the ocean.
超过十亿的鲱鱼会涌入这片海域
Over a billion herring pour into these fields.
蓝色星球Ⅱ的团队耗费三年时间
The Blue Planet II team spent three years
只为记录这一奇观
documenting this astonishing event.
大量的猎物吸引着
Such a wealth of prey attracts predators
数不胜数地捕食者
in extraordinary numbers.
虎鲸
Orcas
和座头鲸
and humpback whales.
但事实上 此类迁徙并不总是如此庞大
But this migration hasn't always been so bountiful.
列夫 诺塔斯泰德是一位挪威的渔业科学家
Leif Notastad is a Norwegian fisheries scientist.
这是几世纪以来 对于整条挪威海岸
It's been one of the most important fisheries
最为重要的捕鱼计划之一
that we had for centuries along the whole coast of Norway.
但在十九世纪六十年代末
But in the late 1960s
这附近的鲱鱼曾濒临灭绝
the herrings that we see around us here was on the brink of collapse.
50年以前 捕鱼行动过于频繁
50 years ago, fishing was so intensive
导致鲱鱼几近消失
that the herring had all but disappeared.
当年 数以千计的虎鲸
Orcas were seen as rivals
因被视作竞争对手而遭到捕杀
and hundreds of them were killed.
直到挪威政府下严令管制后
It was only after the Norwegian government imposed severe restrictions
鲱鱼的数量才开始回升
that the herring began to recover.
这一次 同样也会是一场收获丰盈的捕鱼行动
Today, this is once again an immensely productive fishery,
由科学家密切监视着
closely monitored by teams of scientists.
海洋生物学家伊芙 乔尔戴恩
Marine biologist Eve Jourdain
是一位驻地虎鲸专家
is one of the resident orca experts.
自1982年 虎鲸在挪威被下令保护时起
From 1982, orcas got protected in Norway
这里就拥有了全世界最大的虎鲸种群之一
and we have clearly one of the largest orca population in the world out here.
这里如今有超过一千只虎鲸
There are now over a thousand orcas here.
但恰恰因为这里捕食者众多 包括我们在内
But with so many mouths to feed, including ours,
过去同样的错误能否避免呢
can the mistakes of the past be avoided?
为了回答这个关键的问题
To answer this vital question,
伊芙和她的团队动用了多感官摄像监视器
Eve and her team are using multi sensor camera tags.
通过这些监视器 我们想了解虎鲸是如何与猎物们相互影响的
With the tags we try to see how the orcas interact with their prey.
它们是如何捕猎 如何在水下活动
How they hunt and all about the underwater behaviour
了解一切我们不能从船上观察到的
that we are not able to see from the boat.
监视器必须被安装在
A tag has to be attached
虎鲸身上的某个特定位置
to the orca in exactly the right position.
它来了 它来了
Here it goes. Here it comes.
哦 那一下非常准
Oh, that's a good shot.
这是最不具有侵略性的方式了 那上面是个吸盘
It is the least invasive method. It is suction cups.
所以它不会是在虎鲸身上留下伤痕
So it is not a scratch on the whale afterwards
这一点我们非常欣赏
which is something we really like.
在观察虎鲸期间
While studying the orcas,
伊芙注意到了虎鲸行为上一个令人担忧的改变
Eve noticed a worrying change in their behaviour.
它们已经找到了最轻而易举获得食物的方法
They had worked out the easiest way to get a meal.
我们观察到 虎鲸们只是在等待
EVE: We have seen that the orcas are waiting
那些捕鱼船洒下渔网
for those fishing boats to drop the net.
那渔网好似一个晚餐铃
It acts like a dinner bell
一洒下来 虎鲸就都聚集了过来
and then all the orcas of the area gather.
许多鲱鱼会从渔网缝隙中滑出
Quite a lot of herring slip from the net
虎鲸就会抓紧时间捡漏
and this is exactly what the orcas are looking for.
但如伊芙所见 这种新的捕猎窍门是很危险的
But this new tactic is dangerous, as Eve has witnessed.
我们在那里观测到了虎鲸的行为
We were there to monitor the behaviour of the orcas
它们以漏网之鱼而食
scavenging around the nets.
而且我们还发现 有一只大的成年雄性虎鲸
And we realised that one large adult male
居然被渔网缠住了
was actually trapped inside the net.
当渔民想要收回渔网时
When the fishermen started to retrieve the net
虎鲸显然开始慌了
the orca was obviously starting to panic
他在拼尽全力拉拽渔网
and trying to pull as much as he could.
这只虎鲸真的是在为自己的生命而战
This orca was really fighting for his life.
根据条令 渔民必须在得到批准后
Stringent rules require fishermen
才能打开渔网
to get permission before they open their nets.
但获得审批需要时间
But that took time.
等待的过程真的很漫长
EVE: It was such a long process.
我们都以为那头虎鲸要力竭而亡了
We thought that the whale was going to die of exhaustion.
幸运的是 渔民终于获得了批准
Thankfully, the fishermen finally got the clearance
解开渔网 并释放了精疲力尽的虎鲸
to release their net freeing the exhausted orca.
看到它终于存活了下来 回到了族群里
It was a huge relief to see that this orca made it until the end
我们都长舒了一口气
and finally got back to his family.
当海洋哺乳动物与人类存在直接竞争关系时
With marine mammals and humans competing so directly
此类意外是不可避免的
accidents are inevitable.
一只虎鲸被跟踪两天后
Two days after tagging an orca,
它身上跟踪器脱落 伊芙会将它回收
it's released and Eve collects it.
你知道的 这只跟踪器里全是秘密
This tag is full of secrets, you know,
因为它已经追踪虎鲸几天了
because it has been on the whale for several days
它将会完全展示这只虎鲸的所有行踪
and will just reveal exactly what the whales have been doing.
虎鲸的捕猎技巧在影像里完整展现
Pictures from the tag reveal the hunting technique in detail.
它们会潜入鱼群下方
They dive below the ball of fish
然后做一个后空翻
and then back flip.
用尾巴打晕鱼群中的鱼
The tail slap stuns the herring.
伊芙甚至可以数清虎鲸会吃掉多少鲱鱼
Eve can even work out how many fish the orcas are taking.
单单一次甩尾 它们就能杀死近30只鲱鱼
EVE: They can kill up to 30 herring with just one tail slap.
更令人惊讶的是
And then what is pretty amazing is
捕食团队里的虎鲸会一起分享死鱼
all the individuals of the group share the dead herring.
而这里的捕食者 也并不是只有虎鲸
And it's not just the orcas feeding here...
座头鲸也被这场盛宴吸引而来
Humpback whales are also drawn to the feast.
它们也会被摄像头所监视
They too are being tagged and monitored
渔业科学家列夫便能从中
giving fishery scientist Leif
准确得知它们吃了多少鲱鱼
a complete picture of how much herring is being eaten.
鲸鱼们捕食的数量不到鲱鱼总量的1%
The whales, they take probably less than 1%.
渔民的捕量不超过10%
The fishermen take less than 10%.
所以这里的生态平衡是有足够保障的
So the balance there is that there is enough for everybody.
只要我们能继续保持
Given that we manage to stock in sustainable
长期可持续的发展方法
and a long term sustainable way.
但据估 有将近三分之一的海洋渔场
But it's estimated that almost a third of ocean fisheries
正在被过度打捞
are being over exploited.
这里鲱鱼数量上的显著恢复就证明了
The remarkable recovery of the herring here
一个渔场是可以被精心管理 重回生机的
demonstrates what can happen if a fishery is carefully managed.
我们粗鲁对待海洋有很多负面影响
Our maltreatment of the seas has many effects.
有一些是可以推测的
Some are predictable,
但还有一些是完全出人意料的
but there are others that are rather more surprising.
东南亚
Southeast Asia.
这里的珊瑚礁是全世界最丰富的
The coral reefs here are among the richest on the planet.
海洋生物学家史蒂夫 辛普森
Marine biologist Steve Simpson,
正在探索 声音对于
is discovering how important sound is
住在繁荣珊瑚区的动物有多重要
to the animals that live in these bustling coral cities.
直到现在 通过聆听海底 我们才意识到
STEVE: We're only now just realising by listening underwater
鱼儿们在发出各种各样的声音
that the fish are making all these sounds.
它们用声音求偶
They use sound to attract a mate.
用声音尝试着吓跑捕食者
To try and scare away a predator.
你能听到爆裂声 咕哝声 咯咯声 以及噼啪声
You hear pops and grunts and gurgles and snaps.
海底蕴藏着一整套
There's a whole language underwater
我们才刚刚开始了解的语音
that we're only just starting to get a handle on.
利用先进的多方位水下声音探测器
Using an advanced multi directional hydrophone,
史蒂夫想用通过分辨每种声音的来源
Steve is trying to make sense of this extraordinary chorus
来了解这个非凡的合唱团
by working out who is making which noise.
有一种鱼尤其健谈
One fish is especially talkative.
它们应该是珊瑚礁里最著名的居民
It's perhaps the reef's most famous resident.
小丑鱼
The clownfish.
在拍摄此系列时
While filming for the series,
我们锁定了鞍背小丑鱼一家
we followed this particular family of saddleback clownfish
跟随它们一起搜寻产卵的合适场所
as they search for a suitable place to lay their eggs.
真的是挺闹腾的
It's a noisy affair.
对于小丑鱼 声音代表了一切
For clownfish sound really is everything.
它们整天都在相互交谈
They spend all day talking to each other.
有指挥的语气 也有服从的口吻
You've got dominance and submission.
你能听到各式各样的呼唤
You've got all the others calling to each other.
它们似乎也用声音保护自己
It seems that they also use sound
免受来自珊瑚礁附近狩猎者的侵犯
in protecting themselves from the many predators that hunt around the reef.
包括珊瑚石斑鱼
Including coral trout.
这个鳟鱼道具会骗到小丑鱼吗
Will this model trout fool the clownfish?
它们几乎立即有了反应
They react almost immediately.
开始模仿捕食者
By mimicking a predator,
史蒂夫在不威胁它们生存的前提下 设法记录他们的警报语言
Steve manages to record their alarm calls without putting them at risk.
当雌性小丑鱼试图吓跑珊瑚珊瑚石斑鱼时
You can really hear the deeper pulsing sound of the female
你能听到她更深沉的脉冲音波
as she tries to scare the coral trout away.
而所有孩子只是跳出来 不断跳跃 跳跃 跳跃
And all the little ones are just popping... Pop, pop, pop.
仿佛在说 我很好 我还活着呢
As if to say, "I'm still okay. I'm still alive."
它们为了保护自己的家园
So they've got this real language of sounds that they're using
已经掌握了这种真实存在的语言 去抵抗珊瑚珊瑚石斑鱼的入侵
just to try and defend the colony against this coral trout.
但这一发现引发了我们深深的担忧
But that discovery has led to a serious worry.
这些鱼真的把掠食者吓跑了
The fish were really popping away at the predator.
但是 一旦船过来 它们就显得无所适从
But as soon as the boat came over they looked completely distracted.
这所有的噪音完全改变了鱼类的行为
With all that noise it completely changed how the fish were behaving.
它们无法发出比船更大的声音
Unable to make themselves heard above the noise of boats,
家人们不能再互相发出危险警报
the family can't warn each other of danger.
所以他们现在很容易受到攻击
And so they are now vulnerable to attack.
你可以想想有多少船正在驶过
You think about how many boats are driving around.
所有的船只 所有的海上钻井
All of the ships, all of the offshore drilling.
我们在海洋中产生的所有噪音
All the noise that we're making in the ocean
你就能意识到我们淹没了多少
you realise just how much we're drowning out
这种自然界生物所发出声音
this natural biological noise,
并掠夺了动物们交流的能力
robbing animals of their ability to be able to talk to each other.
所有的噪音都可能对许多珊瑚礁鱼造成严重的困扰
All this noise may have serious consequences for many reef fish
这是因为所有的鱼宝宝们 自孵出之时就被卷入海中
because their babies, as soon as they hatch are swept out to sea.
在那里 它们长到足够强壮 才能回来
There they feed and grow until strong enough to swim back.
而它们正是用声音寻找礁石
And to find the reef, they use sound.
它们会倾听 捕捉所有它们能听到的声音
They listen in. They eavesdrop to the noises that they can hear
并使用这一技能 去选择在哪块礁石上建造自己的家园
and they use that to choose which reef they want to make their home.
但显然我们给海洋带来如此多的噪音
But obviously because we're adding all this noise to the ocean
它们如果还能听到礁石的声音 那就真是奇迹了
it's a wonder whether they can even hear the reef at all.
人为的噪音现今已经遍布整个海域
Man-made noise is now everywhere in the ocean.
对所有的海洋生物都产生了影响
And it has an effect on marine creatures of all kinds.
小至小型鱼
From tiny fish
大到鲸类
to gigantic whales.
但史蒂夫相信会有解决的办法
But Steve believes there are solutions.
海洋噪音确实是个问题
Noise in the ocean is a real problem.
但有些事情我们是可以控制的
But, it's something that we can control.
我们可以选择在何时发出噪音
We can choose where we make the noise.
何地发出噪音
We can choose when we make the noise.
我们也可以直接减少我们制造的噪音量
We can directly reduce the amount of noise that we make
并且我们可以从此刻就做起
and we can start doing that today.
直到现在 我们才开始认识
We're only now beginning to realise
我们制造的声音 对海洋居民造成了什么样的影响
what an impact our noise is having on the inhabitants of the ocean.
其它形式的污染就再熟悉不过了
Other forms of pollution are only too familiar.
塑料问世的一百多年来
Since its invention some hundred years ago,
已经成为我们日常生活中不可或缺的一部分
plastic has become an integral part of our daily lives.
但是 每年约有八百万吨的的塑料
But every year, some eight million tonnes of it
进入海洋中
ends up in the ocean.
而在海中 这些塑料是致命的
And there, it could be lethal.
在蓝色星球Ⅱ的拍摄过程中
While filming Blue Planet II,
船员在每个海域都发现了塑料
the crews found plastic in every ocean.
甚至在最偏远的地方
Even in the most remote locations.
南乔治亚岛
South Georgia.
在南极洲以北900英里处
900 miles north of Antarctica,
这片孤立的荒野
this isolated wilderness is the breeding place
是众多企鹅和象海豹的栖息地
for vast numbers of penguins and elephant seals.
也是空中体形最大的鸟类(信天翁)
It's also a favourite nesting site
最爱的筑巢之地
for the largest bird in the sky.
这是只漂泊的信天翁
A wandering albatross.
在这里 我们了解到远古父母竭尽所能
Here we learn of the extraordinary lengths
给自己的孩子提供最佳的生存机遇
ancient parents go to give their chicks the best chance of survival.
每个伟大的父母都跋涉到千里之外 寻找鱼类和鱿鱼
Each devoted parent travels thousands of miles searching for fish and squid
来喂养它们的孩子
to feed their hungry chick.
尽管它们已竭尽全力
But despite all their efforts,
信天翁的家园仍然陷入了困境
the albatross colony here is in trouble.
露西 奎因是英国南极考察队的一员
Lucy Quinn is part of the British Antarctic Survey team
四十多年来 一直在研究这里的鸟类
studying the birds here for the last 40 years.
只有经过长期的研究
Its only through looking at long terms studies
你才能真正了解这里的生物
that you get a sense of these creatures.
这里的信天翁 在过去的十年里 数量一直在减少
And the albatrosses here have, over the past 10 years, been in decline.
可能有这么几个原因
There are a number of possible reasons.
在海上觅食时
While foraging at sea,
信天翁会被渔具纠缠导致溺死
albatross can get entangled and drowned by fishing gear.
让露西更为担忧的是
But Lucy is particularly alarmed
这些父母究竟为它们的孩子们带回了什么
by what the parents are bringing back for their chick.
信天翁能够咳出
Albatrosses have the ability to cough up
一些不消化的食物
bits of food that they can't digest.
从中我们可以知道它们在吃什么
And from that we can tell what they've been eating.
一只健康小信天翁的饮食中 应该有像鱿鱼之类的食物
A healthy albatross chick in its diet should really have things like squid.
所以我们可以从中找到鱿鱼喙
So we can find the squid beaks that come out of the pellet.
也可以找到一些鱼骨
And also things like fish so we can find fish bones as well.
但这些小信天翁也在被喂食一些 不同寻常的食物
But these chicks are being fed something very different.
我们会发现塑料 这些可怜的雏鸟不得不将这些咳出来
We have some plastic that this poor chick has had to bring up.
塑料袋
Plastic bag.
这是些食品包装袋 看起来像是米饭
Here we have some food packaging. Looks like rice.
幸运的是 这只雏鸟还能把它吐出来
Luckily for this chick, he has managed to get this out of his stomach.
保佑他在换上新羽之前
So, fingers crossed he doesn't have any more plastic left in there
别再吞食更多的塑料了
before he fledges.
对其他雏鸟而言 塑料是可以致命的
For other chicks, plastic can be fatal.
不幸的是 有个塑料牙签
Unfortunately, there is a plastic toothpick
已经穿透这只鸟的胃部
that have actually gone through the stomach.
这么小小的一个东西 实际上就是杀死这只鸟的凶器
Something just as small as that has actually has managed to kill the bird.
看到这些真的很难过
It's really sad to see.
露西收集并记录她在鸟巢周围发现的塑料
Lucy collects and records what plastic she finds around the nests.
这些是上个季度以来 被小鸟吐出来的一些塑料
These are items that were regurgitated just from last season.
这只是其中很小的一部分 实际数量要多得多
And that's gonna be a vast underestimation
因为这些 只是我们碰巧找到的
because that's just ones that we happen to find.
我们没能找到的 还有更多
There'll be many more that we never see being brought back.
为了弄清楚这些垃圾是从哪里来的
To find out where all this rubbish is coming from,
露西和她的团队 在成年鸟类身上 安装了GPS追踪器
Lucy and her team have attached GPS trackers to adult birds.
这些显示了它们要到哪里
It's showing where they're going to find food for themselves
为自己也为后代觅食
and to find food to bring back for their chicks.
这向我们证实了 它们可能正在千里之外
It really shows us that they could be picking up plastic
叼起塑料
from thousands of miles away.
塑料来自于被倾倒进海洋的垃圾
Plastics coming from either being dumped at sea
或者来源于人们家中
or also from people's homes.
塑料进入河流 河流汇入大海
Plastic gets into the rivers and then the rivers flow into the sea.
所以这不仅仅是这个偏远地区的问题
So this isn't just a problem around these remote parts.
更是个世界范围的问题
This is happening worldwide.
是我们的垃圾进入了海洋
And it's our rubbish that's going into the oceans.
这个问题需要我们来解决
It's our problem that we need to solve.
在某些海域
In some parts of the ocean,
每平方英里 就有超过一百万个
it's estimated that there are now over one million pieces of plastic
塑料碎片
for every square mile.
而我们才刚刚认识到
And we're only beginning to discover
这对海洋生物造成了多么严重的影响
just how seriously that affects marine life.
在美国东海岸
On the east coast of the United States,
研究人员正在调研小海豚的神秘死亡事件
researchers are investigating the mysterious deaths of young dolphins.
该小组由莱斯利 哈特博士领导
The team is led by Dr Leslie Hart.
它看起来还很年轻
It looks to be a young animal.
可能就一岁多一点
Maybe a little bit over a year.
我们要试着找出 关于它死亡原因的更多信息
So we're gonna try to find out more information on why this dolphin died.
看着这么小的海豚
Looking at young dolphins...
如此年幼的海豚死去 总是让人心碎
The very young dolphins, it's always heart-breaking.
莱斯利采取组织样本
Leslie takes tissue samples.
他们的化学分析可以提供关键的证据
Their chemical analysis could provide crucial evidence.
这些动物体内检出毒素含量之高
We are often shocked by the high levels of toxins
常常使我们震惊
that we detect in these animals.
这些小海豚死去的原因有很多
These young calves are dying for a number of reasons.
但我们怀疑人造毒素才是主要原因
But we suspect man-made toxins are playing a large role.
塑料可能只是问题的一部分
And plastic could be part of the problem.
塑料一旦进入海洋
Once in the ocean,
就会分解成微小的碎片
plastic breaks down into tiny fragments.
微型塑料
Micro plastics.
所有这些已经排入海洋的化工产品
Along with all the industrial chemicals that have drained into the ocean
形成了潜在的毒性环境
these form a potentially toxic soup.
这些极小的生物体
The really small organisms
会误把这些微型塑料当作食物
can mistake these tiny, tiny plastics as food.
更大些的生物吃这些浮游生物
Then the larger organisms eat the plankton.
然后大鱼吃小鱼
Then the larger fish eat the smaller fish,
一直如此下去
and so on and so forth.
海豚处于这条食物链的顶端
Dolphins are at the top of this food chain
我们现在认为污染物可能在它们的组织中富集
and it's now thought that pollutants may be building up in their tissues
毒性大到 幼崽可以被污染的母乳致死的地步
to such a degree that a mother's contaminated milk could kill her calf.
为了拯救所有的海洋生物
Industrial pollution and the discarding of plastic waste
工业污染物和塑料垃圾必须被处理掉
must be tackled for the sake of all life in the ocean.
在世界各地 人们正在致力于
Around the world, people are now devoting their lives
拯救一些濒危的海洋生物
to saving some of the most threatened sea creatures.
正如这里 加勒比地区
As here in the Caribbean.
在这几座岛上
Every year on just a few islands,
每年都会发生些特别的事情
a remarkable event takes place.
夕阳西下时
As the sun sets,
巨型爬行动物爬上岸来
giant reptiles begin to emerge.
这个雄伟的生物正准备
This magnificent creature preparing...
正准备下蛋
Preparing to lay her eggs
这是所有海龟中体形最大的
is the largest of all turtles.
棱皮龟
A leatherback.
它们可以长到半吨
They can grow up to half a tonne in weight.
并有着可以追溯到一亿年前
And they have an ancestry that goes back a hundred million years
恐龙时代的血统
to the age of the dinosaur.
但近年来 它们的数量呈毁灭型下降
But in recent times their numbers have fallen catastrophically.
然而 在这里 加勒比地区 事情有了转机
Here, however, in the Caribbean there is hope.
棱皮龟离开大海
Leatherback turtles leave the sea
是为了在干燥的沙子里产卵
in order to lay their eggs in the dry sand.
但离开了水 这些巨大的生物很容易成为偷猎者的目标
But out of water, these huge creatures are easy targets for hunters.
在特立尼达岛上的一个小渔村里
In a small fishing village in Trinidad,
伦 彼得斯就曾亲身经历这些
Len Peters has experienced this first hand.
在我家里 吃海龟肉是很正常的事情
I grew up in a household where the presence of turtle meat was normal.
冰箱里总是装满它们
The fridge was always full of it.
所有人 所有人都抓捕海龟 包括我的父母
Everybody... Everybody harvested turtles, including my parents.
当我终有一天接触到
It's only when I became exposed to things
有关棱皮龟的报告时
that were being published about leatherbacks
才知道它们正濒临灭绝
who were on the verge of extinction.
却无人关心
And nobody cares.
这刺激到了我
That piqued my interest.
伦开始以保护棱皮龟为己任
Len took the leatherback's future into his own hands.
为此 他开始晚间到海滩上巡逻
He began patrolling the beach at night to protect the turtles.
这是个十分有勇气的举动
A brave thing to do.
我们遭到了巨大的阻力
We were met with tremendous resistance.
人们会在夜晚攻击我们
People would pelt us at night.
有人辱骂我
I have had persons insult me.
有人诅咒我
I've had persons curse me.
还有人拿着刀要砍我
I've had persons physically try to wrestle me with a machete.
那真是一段很艰难的时光
So it was really a hostile time back then.
如果伦想要拯救这些海龟
If Len was going to save these turtles
他需要赢得整个村子的支持
he needed to win over the whole community.
我们必须找到办法 让村民们
We had to find a way to get the villagers to benefit
感受到这些动物存在的好处
from the presence of these animals.
他开始鼓励游客到海滩来旅游
He began to encourage tourists to visit the beach
并培训一些村民成为导游
and trained some villagers to be their guides.
为保护海龟的未来
To help secure the turtles' future,
他把信息传递给了下一代
he took the message to the next generation.
棱皮龟最大能长到多大
Now what's... What's the largest size a leatherback can grow to?
嗯 沙妮
Uh, Shanie.
- 2000磅 - 答对了
-2,000 pounds. -That's correct.
棱皮龟能够长到2000磅那么大
Leatherbacks can grow to 2,000 pounds.
那的确是一只大海龟
Well, that's a big turtle.
伦的艰苦努力有了回报
Len's hard work paid off.
现在 人们对待海龟的态度已有了转变
And now, attitudes have changed.
我们花了很长时间才取得村民的支持和信任
It took us a while to reach out to the villagers.
但渐渐地 我们也让他们参与进来
But gradually we got them involved as well.
我们让原本要捕杀动物的偷猎者
We got some of the poachers who would be hunting the animals to
转而投入到物保护计划之中
be part of the conservation programme.
在保护成年海龟的同时
As well as protecting the adult turtles,
团队也收集海龟蛋 涨潮时它们可能会被海水淹没
the team also collect any eggs that might be flooded at high tide.
如果这些蛋过于靠近大海
If the eggs are laid too close to the sea,
我们就重选地点把它们埋好
we relocate the eggs and rebury them.
多亏这个村子的不懈努力
Thanks to the efforts of this community,
这些海龟的命运有了翻天覆地的变化
these turtles have had an extraordinary change in fortune.
这里现在被认为是世界上
This is now thought to be one of the densest
最密集的棱皮龟筑巢海滩
leatherback nesting beaches in the world.
在筑巢季的高峰开始时
When we started at the height of the nesting season,
每晚会有30到40只海龟来到这里
the numbers will be 30-40 turtles a night.
现在 已经超过500只了
Now, it's over 500.
在二十年里 我们见证了从每晚的40只
So, we have seen an increase from 40 turtles
到500只海龟的增长
to 500 turtles a night in just around 20 years.
同时也向珍贵的新生小海龟们施以援手
Precious new hatchlings are also given a helping hand.
所有在白天出生的小海龟都会被收集起来
Any that emerge during the day are collected
放归大海 远离饥饿的鸟类
to be released safely back to the sea, away from hungry birds.
待它成年 回归这片孵化它的海滩之前
This little leatherback will have to face a thousand hazards
这只小棱皮龟将会面对千难万险
before it returns as an adult to this beach where it hatched.
而随着人类加剧对海洋的破坏
And those dangers will be greatly increased
这些凶险将会大大增加
because of damage that we have done to the ocean.
祝你好运 小棱皮龟
Good luck, little leatherback.
保护海滩上的繁殖地
Protecting breeding sites on beaches
能够改善一些海洋动物的命运
may improve the fortune of some marine animals,
但当它们在深海中漫游时 提供保护则要困难得多
but safeguarding them while they roam the high seas is much more difficult.
在这里 几乎无法获得保护
Out here, there is little protection.
每个夜晚 数千英里的鱼线上挂满了鱼钩
Every night, thousands of miles of fishing lines laden with hooks are set.
据说 这些鱼线连起来足足能够绕地球两圈
There's enough, it's said, to wrap twice around the world.
大到足以包住大教堂的渔网
Nets large enough to engulf cathedrals
一次可以捕获几百吨鱼
trap hundreds of tonnes of fish at a time.
像鲨鱼这种长途跋涉的旅客尤其危险
Long distance travellers such as sharks are particularly at risk.
据估计 每年大约有几百万只鲨鱼被杀
It's estimated that tens of millions are killed every year,
包括海洋中最大的鱼类 鲸鲨
including the biggest fish in the sea, the whale shark.
鲨鱼生物学家乔纳森 格林担心
Shark biologist Jonathan Green is concerned
留给这些非凡生物的时间已经不多了
that time is running out for these extraordinary creatures.
我们知道它们正在被大规模捕捞
We know that they're being fished possibly at a massive rate.
每年都可能有成千上万的它们被人类捕猎
They may be taken by the thousands, possibly tens of thousands a year.
如果那是真的
If that is indeed true,
我们不知道这种捕鱼压力它们还能承受多久
we don't know how long they can withstand that kind of fishing pressure.
为了拯救它们 乔纳森试着解开
To save them, Jonathan is trying to solve
它们繁衍地点的秘密
the mystery of where they give birth.
并且 第一次 他有了一些确切的线索
And, for the first time, he has a clue as to where this might be.
怀孕的鲸鲨会穿越太平洋
Pregnant whale sharks are thought to be travelling from across the Pacific Ocean
游至加拉帕戈斯群岛中的达尔文岛
to Darwin Island in the Galapagos.
乔纳森打算在一头怀孕的雌性鲸鲨身上
Jonathan is going to try and attach
固定一个多传感器相机
a multi-sensor camera tag to a pregnant female.
好了 准备就绪
Okay. We're good to go.
这些鲨鱼只在那片地区停留几天
These sharks only stay in the area for a few days.
这也许是他唯一的机会
This may be his only chance.
乔纳森必须在鲨鱼潜至危险的深海之前将相机固定好
Jonathan has to attach the tag before the shark dives to dangerous depths.
在自动脱落前
The tag will remain on the giant's fin for two days
相机会在鲨鱼鳍上停留两天
before it's automatically released.
取回来之后 它揭示了一些不寻常的行为
Once retrieved, it reveals some unusual behaviour.
哦 太美了 真美
Oh, beautiful, beautiful.
那有只丝鲨从前面擦过去了 就在她右边
There's a silky rubbing up against the front. Next to her right.
丝鲨在摩擦她粗糙的皮肤
The silky sharks are brushing up against her rough skin,
也许是为了擦掉身上的寄生虫
perhaps to scrape off parasites.
幼鱼无论种类 表层水域都因这些掠食性鲨鱼的存在
These predatory sharks make the surface waters very unsafe places
而变得很不安全
for young fish of any kind.
难题出现了
There is a surprise in store.
跟踪标记的深度传感器显示
The tag's depth sensor reveals that she dived
她潜入了600米深的海中
to a depth of 600 metres.
可下面对于相机来说过于黑暗
But down there, it's too dark for the camera.
乔纳森能够证明它们是否在繁衍的唯一方法
The only way Jonathan can prove if they're giving birth
就是到深海亲自观察
is to go down and look.
一个身影渐渐变得清晰
Out of the gloom, a shape materialises.
另一只大型鲸鲨
Another massive whale shark.
快看看她 她在看我们 她正在看我们
Oh, look at her. She's having a look at us. She's looking right at us.
她真是太大了
She is huge.
看她的肚子 绝对是巨大的
And look at the belly. Absolutely massive.
那是只巨大的雌性怀孕鲸鲨
That's a large pregnant female.
她转身了 她转身了
She's turning around. She's turning around.
这表示我们可以跟着它们 可以在潜艇里跟着它们
Goes to show we can follow them. We can follow them in the submarine.
她带领他们进入了黑暗之中
She leads them down into the darkness.
探测器测量 突破100米 仍在下沉中
Rover control. Passing 100 metres, descending.
一直向下 我想她稍稍加速了
Heading down. I think she's accelerated slightly.
她太快了
She's too fast.
强劲的洋流阻碍了他们 潜艇无法继续前进
And with the strong current running against them, the sub can't keep up.
但是 第一次 乔纳森能够亲眼看见
But, for the first time, Jonathan can see for himself
她前进的目的地
exactly where she's headed.
达尔文岛能够为新生的幼鱼们提供
What specifically Darwin could provide
安全的避难所 捕食者们无法进入
is a safe refuge for those new-born pups where predators can't access.
对于这些穿越大洋的巨人来说
Perfect conditions for the formative years
这里为它们的成长提供了完美的居住环境
of these ocean-travelling giants.
令人难以置信
That was unbelievable.
真是一生的梦想
Dream of a lifetime.
他发现了怀孕的鲸鲨
His discovery that pregnant whale sharks
就在这片深海之中 这是强有力的证据
are visiting this very deep patch of the sea floor
证明这里的确是这些巨人们繁衍下一代的地方
is strong evidence that this is indeed where the giants produce their young.
如果我能证明它们的确出生在这片海域
If I can actually prove that they are giving birth in this area,
我们就拥有了必要的信息
then we'll have the information necessary
可以联系政府 告诉他们
to go to governments and actually say,
"你们必须保护它们迁移的常规路线"
"You must preserve those routes that they're migrating through."
到那时 也只有那时 我们才能真正为这些
And then, and only then, can we really truly afford protection
美丽的大洋旅客提供保护
for this beautiful ocean traveller.
今天 我们只有不到百分之一的
Today, less than one percent
国际水域受到保护
of our international waters are protected.
如果我们要守护多种海洋生物的未来
And the creation of marine reserves is vital
那么海洋保护区的建立就变得至关重要
if we're to safeguard the future of many ocean creatures.
这会需要国际间的合作
It will require international cooperation.
但在这里 也仍有希望
But here, too, there is hope.
我们能够扭转局势
We can turn things around.
我们曾经做过这样的事情
We've done so once before.
几个世纪以来 世界上以海为生的国家
For centuries, the sea-going nations of the world
都在捕杀鲸类 直到它们濒临灭绝
hunted the great whales until they were close to extinction.
之后 在1986年 这些国家一致同意
And then, in 1986, those nations got together
停止商业捕鲸
and agreed to put a stop to commercial whaling.
今天 虽然仍有部分国家继续捕鲸
Today, although a few nations continue to hunt whales,
但有一些鲸数量正在恢复
some of the great whales are making a recovery.
在斯里兰卡周围的热带海域
In the tropical seas surrounding SrI Lanka,
流传着许多有关鲸类聚集的故事
there are stories of vast gatherings of whales.
2009年内战结束后
When the civil war ended in 2009,
当地人重新在这片水域捕鱼
locals here were able once again to fish these waters.
不久这里就有了关于抹香鲸集结的报道
There were soon reports of assemblies of sperm whales,
已有几个世纪都没有见到这种景象了
the likes of which had not been seen for centuries.
海洋向导达亚决心探求
Marine guide Daya was determined to get to the truth
这些渔民故事背后的真相
behind these fishermen's tales.
渔民们告诉我从这里往北一点
The fishermen told me that there are lots of whales
有许多鲸
a little bit north from here.
他们没有告诉我确切的数字
They didn't actually tell me a number,
但数量很大 不止一两只
but in big numbers, not one or twos.
而是有很多
Er, many.
这件事花了他三年时间
It took him three years,
不过最终 他找到了支撑这些传闻的证据
but eventually, he found evidence to support these rumours.
我们看见大约15只抹香鲸从身边经过
We saw about 15 sperm whales go past us.
之后 另外四只也越过我们
Then, another four came past us.
在看见大概40只鲸鱼后 我开始计数
After about 40 then passed me, I started counting.
然而它们接连不断 我都数不过来了
Still, they kept coming, so I lost count.
我估计大概见到了300只抹香鲸
I estimated that we saw about 300 sperm whales.
抹香鲸过去曾遭受大规模捕杀
Sperm whales were once killed in vast numbers
如果这种屠杀仍在继续的话
and it's thought that if the slaughter had continued,
这个物种将会濒临灭绝
the species would be in danger of extermination.
但至少 现在它们仍能在这里以大规模被发现
But now, here at least, they are being seen in huge numbers.
我想它们来这里是为了觅食 交配并养育后代
I believe they come here to feed, mate, and raise their young.
对它们而言这里一定算是个度假区
So, this must be a holiday spot for them, you know.
目前为止 我只知道这世界有这一个地方
At the moment, I don't know of any other place in the world
抹香鲸会有如此大规模的聚集
that, er, sperm whales gather like this.
尽管鲸类数量仍旧在不断衰减
Although some whale populations are still in decline,
但这种景象证明当海洋国家一起努力时
scenes like this prove that when sea-going nations come together,
会产生惊人的结果
they can achieve astonishing results.
但是今天海洋面临着真正全球范围的威胁
But today, the oceans face threats on a truly global scale.
大堡礁
The Great Barrier Reef.
世界上最大的珊瑚礁生态系统
The largest coral reef system in the world.
这里 我们记录的片段展示了鱼类能有多聪明
Here, we filmed stories which reveal just how smart fish can be.
例如 这种机灵的猪齿鱼
This ingenious tuskfish, for example,
用它最喜欢的珊瑚来击开贝类
used a favourite coral anvil to smash open shellfish.
这种奇特的行为曾被
This astonishing behaviour has been closely studied
当地的科学家亚力克斯 维尔 认真的研究过
by local scientist Alex Vail.
我们给它取名叫"珀西" 执着的意思
We're calling Percy "Percy the Persistent"
因为它可能要花一个小时才能敲开第一个贝壳
because he took, like, an hour to open the first shell.
他至少要敲击50次以上
He must have hit it well over 50 times,
不过他依旧会坚持 直到把贝壳砸开
but he just kept on going and finally got it open.
亚力克斯在大堡礁其中一个
Alex grew up on the Great Barrier Reef
叫利泽德的偏远小岛上长大
on one of its more remote islands, Lizard.
他对这里的珊瑚礁非常了解
He knows the reef intimately.
不过 在2016年 拍摄蓝色星球Ⅱ时
But, in 2016, while he was filming for Blue Planet II,
亚力克斯目睹了一场大灾难
Alex witnessed a catastrophe.
拍摄开始的时候 一切都很好
ALEX: When we started filming, everything was pretty much fine.
所有的珊瑚基本都是健康的
All of the corals were basically healthy.
但在最近几周 一切都变了
But in the last few weeks, everything changed.
我之前从未见过这种现象
I have never seen anything like this before.
海洋变暖和一种不可预测的气候事件
A combination of a warming ocean
厄尔尼诺现象的结合
and an unpredictable weather event called El Niño
使海洋温度前所未有地上升
raised sea temperatures to record levels.
这对珊瑚来说是毁灭性的打击
And this had a disastrous effect on the corals.
高温使造礁珊瑚失去了提供营养的藻类
The heat causes reef-building corals to lose their nourishing algae,
白色的骨骼被暴露在外
exposing their white skeletons.
当温度持续上升 白化的珊瑚就会死亡
When temperatures remain high, bleached corals die off.
今年的白化情况是史上最严重的一次
The bleaching this year has been the worst in history
对大堡礁来说
for the Great Barrier Reef.
利泽德岛约九成的
About 90 percent of the branching corals
珊瑚分支都死了
on the reef out here at Lizard Island are dead.
它对另一种生活在这儿的生物
It also has disastrous consequences
也造成了灾难性的后果
for the other creatures that live here.
珀西在那里游泳
Percy swimming around out there.
令人难过的是他的城堡开始白化了
The really sad thing is that his castle's starting to bleach.
如果我们失去了珊瑚礁 我们也很可能会失去猪齿鱼
If we lose our coral, there's a chance we're going to lose our tuskfish
当看到你从小潜水的地方
It's incredibly sad to see areas that you've dived on
变成了一片废墟你真的会感到无比悲伤
since you were a little kid just turn to rubble.
我在面具下哭了 当看到
I cried in my mask, when I saw,
这种严重的白化情况时
you know, some of the devastation from this bleaching.
在过去的三年里
In the last three years,
全世界超过三分之二的珊瑚礁
over two-thirds of the world's coral reefs
被认为在遭受海水升温的影响
are thought to have suffered from rises in ocean temperatures.
这不是它们所面临的唯一挑战
This is not the only challenge they face.
研究表明 海洋中的
Research is revealing how the fundamental
基本化学反应正在改变
chemistry of the ocean is changing.
克里斯 兰登教授通过将稀酸倒在贝壳上向我展示了
Professor Chris Langdon shows me what this might mean
这对于海洋的未来意味着什么
for the future of our seas by pouring dilute acid over shells.
这比我们现在的海洋酸性强多少
And how much more acidic is this than the present ocean?
这个酸性比目前海洋的要强
This is more concentrated than the pH of the ocean
但它加速了这个过程使其变的直观
but it accelerates the process so we can see something visually.
看 这些贝壳发生了什么 它们是由碳酸钙组成的
So, what's happening is, these shells, they're made out of calcium carbonate,
这些酸正在溶解它们
and the acid is dissolving them.
珊瑚礁的组成和这些贝壳的材料是一样的
And coral reefs are made out of the same material as these shells here.
但现在这肯定还没有发生 对吧
But surely this is not happening in the ocean now. Right now?
只是我们现在看到的 要比海洋中实际的强烈而已
What we're seeing here is more dramatic than what's happening in the ocean.
但是贝壳与珊瑚礁确实正在溶解
But the shells and the reefs are really truly dissolving.
到本世纪末 珊瑚礁可能会消失
Coral reefs could be gone by the end of this century.
这种现象的原因是什么 二氧化碳
And the cause of this? Carbon dioxide.
它溶于水 形成碳酸
Dissolved in the sea water, it forms carbonic acid.
大气中的二氧化碳越多
The more carbon dioxide in the atmosphere,
海洋的酸性就越强
the more acidic the ocean becomes.
证据表明化石燃料的燃烧
Evidence points to the burning of fossil fuels
正是二氧化碳含量升高的主要原因
as the primary cause for these increasing levels of carbon dioxide.
毫无疑问这是人类造成的
And this is man-made beyond question.
确实毫无疑问
Beyond question.
但是克里斯认为还为时未晚
But Chris believes all is not lost.
我们最需要做的 就是减少二氧化碳的排放
All we have to do, and I say all, is reduce our CO2 emissions.
我们可以用可再生能源 风能 太阳能
We can switch to renewable fuels, wind and solar,
用来代替天然的矿物材料
instead of natural fossil fuels.
这样 就不会
And so, none of this has to
- 发展成最糟的情况 - 它还可以自我修复是吗
-develop to the worst case. -And that could fix it?
是的 没错 这种情形是否出现在未来 这取决于我们
Yeah, absolutely. So, this future does not have to play out. It's up to us.
随着气候的变化 海洋逐渐变暖
As the climate changes, the seas warm.
我们的海洋受到了严重的影响
Our oceans are being seriously affected.
没有什么地方比两极地区更明显了
And this is nowhere more apparent than at the poles.
南极洲
Antarctica.
对蓝色星球Ⅱ摄制团队来说 这是他们最壮志凌云的探险
For the Blue Planet II team, this was their most ambitious expedition.
史上首次 一艘载人潜水器
For the first time in history, a manned submersible
将会试着潜到水下1000米
will try to dive to a depth of 1,000 metres
到达南极海底
and reach the Antarctic seabed.
一次真正的未知之旅
A true journey into the unknown.
控制探测器 已通过40米 结束
Control rover. Passing 40 metres. Over.
带领团队进行这一历史性潜水的
Leading the team on this historic dive
是深海科学家约翰 柯普利
is deep sea scientist John Copley.
我们第一次看到这种景观
We get our first glimpse of this landscape.
我们周围活跃的生命令人吃惊
And the carpet of life around us is astounding.
太美了
It's beautiful.
载人潜水器中的潜水经历让约翰
Diving in a submersible gives John an entirely new understanding
对这个庞大生态系统的运作有了全新的认识
of how this rich ecosystem works.
还给了他一个难得的机会
But it also offers him a unique opportunity
调查这片海域是如何变化的
to investigate how the ocean here is changing.
我们在观察那里的海洋生物时
While we're observing the marine life down there,
潜水器也在记录周围的环境
the subs are also recording what the environment is like,
我们得到温度 含盐度的测量值
so we're getting measurements of temperature, of salinity.
希望这些数据能够帮助我们弄清
It's hopefully gonna enable us to understand the changes
地球的这个重要地区所正发生的改变
that are happening in this vital part of our planet.
为了得到更清晰的结果
To get a fuller picture, John also lowers
约翰还下放了一个深海温度探测器
a deep sea temperature probe.
他的数据有助于尝试绘制
His data is contributing to an international attempt
国际间海平面与气温共同上升的图表
to chart the rise in both sea and air temperatures.
在这里事物变化速度之快
What shocks me about what all the data show
是数据分析中最令我吃惊的
is how fast things are changing here.
我们正迈向未曾涉足的领域
We're headed into uncharted territory.
为了真正地理解
To truly comprehend
这里温度上升带来的影响
the effect of the temperature increases here,
约翰坐上直升机
John takes to the skies.
从那儿 他能够记录
From here, he can record the number and size
从冰架上崩落的冰山数量和尺寸
of the icebergs being produced as the ice shelves melt and break apart.
周围的冰山能够让我们明白
The bergs we're seeing all around us give you some idea
南极正发生着多么大的变化
of how huge this process is that's taking place on the Antarctic.
随着漂浮的冰架断裂
As the floating shelves break up, they allow water,
会使原本存在了数千年的冰块融化成水
which has been locked up on land as ice for thousands of years,
混入海洋中
to empty into the sea.
据预测这会使海平面升高
And this is predicted to push up sea levels.
冰架崩解 等于打开了泄洪闸
If the ice shelves break up, then that opens the flood gates.
陆地上的冰会更快的流入海中
Ice on land flows faster into the sea
使海平面上升
and that's what pushes up the sea levels.
所以 这里发生的一切影响着我们所有人
So, what's happening here right now affects all of us.
像迈阿密一样的城市已经处于威胁之中了
Already, cities like MiamI here are under threat.
科学家们预测 到本世纪末
Scientists predict that by the end of the century,
海平面将会上升一米甚至两米
the sea levels could have risen by a metre or even two.
一旦成真 这座城市将会部分沉入水下
Were that to happen, parts of this city would certainly be submerged.
全世界有亿万人住在海岸附近
Around the world, hundreds of millions of people live near the coast,
由于海平面上升 他们的生活会受到严重影响
and as sea levels rise, their lives will be seriously affected.
很明显我们的行动对世界海洋
It's now clear that our actions are having a significant impact
有着巨大影响
on the world's oceans.
在摄制这个系列纪录片的四年里
During the four years it took to make this series,
我们最先见证了很多环境变化
we've witnessed many of these changes first-hand.
但我们也和为了保卫海洋未来
But we've also worked alongside men and women
而无私奉献的人们一同奋斗过
dedicating their lives to safeguarding the ocean's future.
海洋为我们提供氧气
The oceans provide us with oxygen,
调节气温
they regulate temperature,
为我们提供食物和能源
they provide us with food and energy supplies.
一个失去健康海洋的世界是不堪设想的
And it's unthinkable to have a world without a healthy ocean.
我仍然相信我们有能力
I still think we have the capability
去改变我们的行为 不再浪费资源
to change the manner in which we're wasting resources,
毒害海洋
in which we're poisoning our oceans,
就能期待一个有着健康海洋的未来
and we can look to a future with healthy oceans.
我期许 我相信我们的所作所为
When I look forward, I believe that if what we are doing
只要能被稍微效仿些许
can be duplicated just a little bit.
这些动物们就有活下来的机会
These animals will have a chance of surviving.
我想 这要取决于我们每个人
It comes down, I think, to us each taking responsibility
为自己的选择承担责任
for the personal choices that we make in our everyday lives.
希望我们每个人都能做到
That's all any of us can be expected to do.
每天的选择累积起来就会有改变
And it is those everyday choices that add up.
我们正处在历史上独一无二的时期
We are at a unique stage in our history.
在此之前我们从未如此深刻地
Never before have we had such an awareness
意识到我们在对这个星球做些什么
of what we are doing to the planet.
之前我们也从未有过这样的力量去改变这种状况
And never before have we had the power to do something about that.
毫无疑问 我们肩负着保护这个蓝色星球的责任
Surely, we have a responsibility to care for our blue planet.
人类的未来
The future of humanity,
以及地球上所有的生命
and indeed all life on Earth,
此刻 都悬于我们一念之间
now depends on us.
解说：大卫·爱登堡
Translated by
CATHY & GRAPE
翻译：Cathy & 葡萄
Translated by
PINASTER & CICADA
翻译：嵩下小松树 & 知了
Supervised by
VERONICA
监制:斑斑
Proofreaded by
CANNAE & WILDER
校对：歪二德 & AlexaJU
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER FROM SHOU
特效：歪二德
我
们
的
蓝
色
星
球
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(斯里兰卡内战:1983年7月爆发.交战双方主要是斯里兰卡政府和泰米尔伊拉姆猛虎解放组织)
(此为双髻鲨,又称锤头鲨,两眼间的距离可达1米)